howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com
that's Jim ruts show calm days guest is
John rabe regular a guest on our show
John's a thinker and writer about global
level systems and conflicts his main
platform is global guerillas on patreon
you can google it or you can find the
link on this podcast episode page at Jim
rut comm I've been a longtime
contributor to John's support on patreon
and I'd encourage you to do so - we
don't have independent voices like this
if we don't reach into our pockets and
help them make a living so John let's
jump into a couple of three things that
you've talked about over the last few
days on your very interesting Twitter
stream the first is very interesting
development the website defeat disinfo
org has sprung up and frankly I
predicted something like this back in
2012 you know tell us about what defeat
this info org is and what do you think
the implications are well it's built on
the same kind of software that was
developed to run counter narrative
efforts against terrorists groups there
were a lot of efforts undertaken over
the last decade or so particularly you
know in response to Isis trying to you
know run counter narrative and you know
that there's lots of companies involved
in that - I mean there's a Google wing
more sub venture that that that focuses
on that it's basically a kind of system
that when it sees a narrative develop
that could you know promote a terrorist
group
it would then counter that narrative
quickly and you know spread that in from
you know the counter narrative out to a
lot of influencers and in this case
defeat disinfo is is focused on
Republicans and Trump so for example if
Trump says something like why don't you
take disinfectant internally they would
run a counter narrative and then you
know spread out the the information or
that the pandemic is similar to the flu
they would run a counter narrative
against that yeah so that's it in a
nutshell oh and then the key part at
least as I saw it is that they're
recruiting an army of people to be their
spreaders right they don't seem to use
BOTS per se but rather they are
organizing a decentralized narrative
multi broadcast point with potentially
hundreds of thousands of people who are
taking their you know counter arguments
and posting them in a fairly regimented
and highly automated way by the way on
Twitter and Facebook and various other
platforms emailing them to people etc
and so this essentially automating and
organizing what's been happening in a an
automated and disorganized way by a you
know propagation of memes with links
across social media and email well it's
it's focusing on getting those key
influencers those independent
influencers to retweet the counter
narrative and or to post about it or
write about it and I mean recruiting an
army of people to make that possible or
you know to distribute the information
and get it into the hands of those key
influencers is a it's just a way of
working around the rules at Twitter and
other sites have you know blocking BOTS
what they're looking for is what they
call a inauthentic communication in
authentic posts whatever that means so
this is a way of working around that if
you give a lot of people enlisted to do
this and you can you can avoid getting
snagged by those rules at least probably
maybe they'll say collusion we
saw a hundred we just saw 17,000
retweets of the same post or the or of
the same link seems improbable us we'll
see if there if there's a counter arms
race against this oh yeah well most
definitely there will be I mean it's
kind of like IEDs and in counter IEDs
you know there's an innovation and ID
design and then there's a counter that
comes out months later six months later
and then two weeks later there's another
innovation that neutralizes the the the
counter IAD work so you know this is it
definitely an arms race it's it's a
global information war it's it's an
interesting maybe direction for where
parties are going you know political
parties political networks are you know
recruiting you know tens of thousands if
not millions of people to amplify a
message yep to get it out and and doing
it in a formalized way I mean you know
that's how parties evolve online is that
they they used to do it through
influencing news coverage and now
recruiting a million people to amplify a
message and doing it in a formal way is
probably how they earn their support
yeah seems like you know again I think I
wrote about this in 2012 and a document
not this exact form but the idea of sort
of discipline organized mimetic armies
and we mentioned offense defense arms
race which will certainly happen for
Julie the Twitter's and Facebook's will
try to down-regulate these messages but
obviously platforms like this will try
to work around that but the other which
I think is perhaps more interesting and
gets to what you're talking about about
this might be the politics of the future
is the offense offense arms race where
let's say these anti Trump folks build
up their army of 25,000 the Trump stirs
then build up their arm you have 200,000
right and and so as you as you indicate
this could be the future of how the
parties actually communicate and as we
know online this course is way less
discipline can turn way uglier
that's a controlling mainstream media
and the thing that came to my mind is
let's let's think this arms race going
through two or three
cycles here and of course in internet
time two or three cycles might be
between now and September and you know
what it might look like is Germany in
1932 where the various right-wing and
write populist parties and communists
and far-left parties which there were
several were actually engaged in
murderous street brawls all over Germany
at you know hundreds of people a month
were dying in really ugly fighting in a
more or less quasi organized and in some
cases even paid political street
fighters essentially this is this could
be what we're this could be what we're
heading for some real ugly real ugly
stuff with sort of quasi organized brown
shirts versus red shirts I have a whole
report on that actually but that that
looked at the anti five versus the
outright battle street battles and then
I wrote a whole report looking at what
happened in Germany on the street level
all right from so how that will put a
post up on that link on that our site I
also wrote a short story called blood in
the streets back in 2017 which talks
about sort of an Tifa versus more or
less legitimate Trump rallies spiraling
out of control into violence you know it
has actually turned out that way yet but
it gives it gives an indication so I
think you know we all thinking about
this and I have some kind of a subtle
critique of the whole approach though
and it was kind of a built on my my
thinking about how it was used in the
counterterrorism space is that them it's
it's not as effective as people would
think it is because I mean Trump's
approach or the the sense approach in
general is more maneuver based it's it's
disruption it it disrupts cognitive
function and then countering it quickly
isn't as effective in in blunting that I
mean the damage is already done and a
subset of those people actually see the
the counter it might be good at
potentially keeping the you know
grooming the in-group and keeping them
cognitively whole in the face of this
disruption so they don't feel like
they're constantly outgunned but in
terms of a
it's general effect I think it's going
to be pretty weak I think in terms of
promoting a consensus which is the
opposite of the you know the other
political party or whoever that
political party is is the best way to
promote the consensus is to solve the
problem the consensus was formed around
and you know if you're moving that
forward if you're solving those problems
then you're growing your consensus and
that's the biggest failure that the
Democrats have had and this instance is
that they have not jumped in front of
solving the pandemic I mean completely
abdicated it and they're not moving that
consensus forward or whoever if whether
it's Democrats or anybody who stood in
front of this and actually said okay
let's coordinate the efforts to get this
thing solved well the Democratic
governors are doing a reasonably good
job certainly better than the real look
at governor's on a state-by-state basis
but there's a you know there's a natural
plan we talked last time about a kind of
a doing that kind of national broadcast
taking in all these open source efforts
you know there's there's lots of cool
stuff that could be done I mean you know
we're talking this morning or I was
talking to some people this morning
about the National Guard being mobilized
and there's more National Guard being
already mobilized in the United States
and the Canadian and UK military's
combined it's it's been a huge
mobilization that's going through the
end of June and there's a kind of a
slight I mean these these these Guard
soldiers are out there you know at the
meatpacking plants and in other places
you know critical infrastructure that's
been you know taken down because of the
pandemic and there's you know supporting
the kind of reboot of this
infrastructure and it occurred to me
that you know there's a whole new space
that could be developed kind of a
universal guard a Swiss Army knife of a
mobilization that where you bring a
group of people that are have the
capacity and the ability to learn
quickly and and the willingness to work
hard and those people could be mobilized
and once you've you know kind of vetted
the list and those people could be
mobilized to come into a situation and
get that infrastructure going again and
this works at the national scale or
maybe even at the community scale where
you have a group of people that have
these kind of you know array of
subspecialties and or just a billet II
to learn quickly I mean now that with we
have access to all this information if
you have the ability to learn quickly
you can boot yourself up really quick
you know very very fast and then get
them to come in and get a factory going
again and getting the PPP on or PPE on
and and and and in doing it in a safe
way until the the regular workforce can
come back in and you can see this you
know that could that could be kind of
force that would really be something
that could be coordinated a national
level but you know there's this moving
the the solution set forward is really
the way to kind of consolidate the
consensus thing and make it feel like
it's actually moving in a direction that
has some kind of positive conclusion and
that grows it that grows the the center
of gravity makes it you know increases
the attraction of it and accumulates
more people and pulls them out of the
descent you could imagine this little
Swiss Army knife militia being
unofficial you know being say an arm of
the Democratic Party for instance it
could be I mean you think of it also at
the local level is is you have lots of
critical infrastructure that could be
taken down and and and knowing or
assembling a group of people that can
they can can do that that that have been
vetted and vouched for and are willing
to you know pitch in and come in and do
the what's necessary to actually you
know boot that piece of infrastructure
back up after it's been shut down it's
even a more powerful if they if the you
know local government willing to fund it
so you know willing to pay the people to
come in and do this so you can get all
these like positive cycles of
reinforcement if you can get it get it
going it makes a lot of sense let's move
on to our next topic something you've
written about recently you know the
economic shitstorm that's about the land
or his head has been landing and will
become more obvious in about a month is
going to prune the economic field
there's gonna be winners and there's
gonna be losers any thoughts on how we
might think about who are likely to be
the winners we're going to be the losers
who are gonna be least relatively
stronger against their competition on
the
backside of this thing right yeah well
there that there's the pure-play
companies that are only only viable in
the pandemic when things are shut down
and then there's the ones that can
straddle both sides you know my son's
company codecademy he's his company
straddles both sides they make money
when their they've been making money
when they're there is an append emic and
they'll make money they're making more
money now that there is so they you know
they can handle both conditions Amazon
certainly in that camp the strongest the
strongest players will be the ones that
can you know handle coming out of the
pandemic as well as they're making a lot
of money right now during the pandemic
I mean Amazon added what a hundred and
seventy-five thousand employees in the
last couple months
so they're making a money hand over fist
on this my bigger worry is more like is
that the you know US government is at
risk here because we're benefiting right
now from this flight to safety it's
keeping our borrowing rates in the
cellar I mean it's really cheap to
borrow right now for the US and if this
persists and if this crisis persists and
and and you know relative to everywhere
else it may be something that the
reverses and that will see people
fleeing the united states and fleeing
the dollar and driving up our rates and
that could cause a whole cascade of
problems for us yeah that's that problem
is sitting out there for a long time
this epoch of cheap money for federal
borrowing is the only thing that keeps
our even previous stack of debt at 20
trillion dollars from crushing us if we
paid the the historical average federal
front funds rate which is about five
percent across all averaged across all
maturities you know we'd be laying out
something about seventy percent of
income tax receipts just on interest
right and so this you know this sword of
damocles has been hanging over us for a
long while and it could be particularly
if we miss play both the public health
side which it looks like there's some
chance that we're doing and the fiscal
side
we could be in a world of hurt we may
lose our status as the world's reserve
currency yeah there's there's benefits
to cohesion and stability and being the
most cohesive and most stable country of
any size for for a long time as has
yielded us you know incredible benefits
as the world became on more unstable and
more chaotic but if that reverses at all
oh boy the decline can be very very
quickly yeah I could be a phase change
as we'd say in complexity science where
we go from the perception of high
cohesion and coherence which frankly has
probably not really been true for the
last 10 or 15 years to a state where
people recognize the fact that the u.s.
is in a bad way and more or less
dysfunctional even though again I would
point to the fact that it probably has
been dysfunctional for 15 years but
people weren't really aware of it yet
yeah that's it's a it goes back to my
challenge for the 21st century at least
for nation-states is to maintain
cohesion in the face of a complex world
yeah we're just throwing off you know
complex crises again and at you know one
after another
I mean first 9/11 and then the financial
crisis and and now this I mean a crisis
that has embedded nonlinearities and and
has lots of uncertainties and even if
you dig into it you'll uncover even more
uncertainty you know that's the thing
that actually turns a crisis that you
know people talk about predicting the
pandemic and and you can predict the
kind of broad outline of a pandemic but
the one that really gets you is the
complex one and the one that keeps on
giving
I mean even if you're even if you know
it's what it is and and how it operates
you still can't deal with all the
complexity that you're being faced with
it's constantly changing and the
challenge is is ongoing and it does so
much damage over so much time that you
end up seeing massive change in the
social structures that are built to
confront it and we saw that with 9/11
yielded the G watt the Global War on
Terror and yielded all sorts of changes
to the US government terms of
militarizing police and etc and spending
gobs of money six trillion dollars on
Wars that we shouldn't have spent and
then the financial crisis obviously did
a lot in terms of D little izing the
government in German you know it's an
inability to actually punish the people
who committed the FRA
so these complex situations are these
complex threats can can can keep on
giving over decades yeah and then this
is a very very important point you're
hitting here on John which is frankly no
country on earth is actually very good
at dealing with complex situations you
know nonlinear embedded nonlinearities
without the complete set of data in fact
the usual real world big problem you
only have part of the data you know for
instance the pandemic well we knew
pandemics happen just look at the the
occurrence rate you know about one every
ten years but what are the parameter
settings this one happened to have a set
of parameter settings that people hadn't
thought of which is sort of just lethal
enough as we talked about last time to
be very scary and disturbing but not
murderously lethal like MERS or
something but highly highly contagious
asymptomatic so it's essentially
parameter space suspect I'm working on
an essay right now I'd love to send you
a copy of it for your thoughts before I
actually publish it asking the US
government to establish a department of
wicked risks where we actually build up
the capability of complexity science
modelers Network theorists etc and and
can think of it almost like a planning
staff like the military has but for the
civilian sector which will enumerate as
many known
categories of potential wicked risk like
pandemics like solar flares
you know several others which I
enumerate and does some probing with
leading edge thinkers for all right what
about what unknown unknowns could could
become known or at least speculated
apart and have act and then would
actually build models that are
parameterised for as many of these
situations as they could afford and you
know so that again complex thinking does
not come naturally to humans we weren't
raised in a world where high
nonlinearities that play out over short
periods of time really impact that our
lives very often may be a forest fire
like that but not too often and now our
societies are going to be put at risk of
at least extreme damage if not actual
collapse by one wicked risk after
another and it seems to me just like we
have a Department of Defense we also
have to have a department of wicked
risks yeah and a lot of this stuff has
to do with them changing our perspective
on response and and you know we we try
to solve these problems with with
traditional thinking and it just doesn't
work I mean for instance that the way in
which we shut down international borders
women were slow and methodical and we do
try to do it selectively but with this
kind of threat you have to do it quickly
and all at once yep because they're so
easy to route around but you know it's
these assumptions that we have about how
things operate and and that we can
optimize the solution and that you know
there's a way to kind of target the
bailout money or that we should do it
higher in the stack and focusing on
corporations versus individuals I mean
all of these things are clearly mistakes
if you look at it from a holistic
perspective and looking at it from a
perspective of complexities just it's a
different kind of assumptions that you
know we don't know the particulars of
any given crisis in you know what we do
have the ability to develop a kind of a
general response methodology a way of
kind of responding to these things that
that you know that kind of that kind of
a crisis group that you were talking
about you know just no notice the kind
of gut level instinct as to what
direction who we should be heading into
and can simulate it right maybe yeah
that was one thing but having mature
various teams usually we know what's
like in climate change different models
give different results but when you have
an ensemble of models created
independently that gives similar results
it gives a lot of confidence in in the
situation so I would imagine this
department not only having its own
modelers but also being a fairly
significant source of funding to
academic researchers to build models
using entirely fresh code code bases
entirely fresh ideas and have those
models up and running and be ready to go
at need rather than you know the the you
know the very halting and whole series
of bad decisions that we see made and oh
by the way it did turn out that there
was one simple way to partially at least
tame the pandemic on the front end which
was social distancing yeah and those
come those countries that were willing
to do it firmly and hard unlike the
United States I've actually really
pushed their case countdown but the
backsides gonna be way more complicated
this is not just one simple rubber
mallet right now we're gonna have to
manage contact tracing escalated and
testing and not only escalating testing
but then optimizing how do you use the
test do you use them on people high
probability of being sick or do you use
part of that as a background
instrumentation to see your base case
rates right you want to do both but our
current people capable of thinking like
that I don't know you know and the
coupling between the public health
problems and the economic problems are
classic nonlinear coupled systems which
are I hate to say it beyond the
cognitive ability at least the people I
see at the highest levels of our
government so these are gonna be you
know challenges that that are this will
not be the last time we face this so
this may be one of the great exemplars
which allows us to think about how we
should build some institutional response
for the future yeah I think the the
modeling aspect of this is great at the
at the very very early warning grate and
then once you identified that this is a
complex threat then you go okay what
quick frames can we put on this to make
some immediate decisions and then you do
the more complex or more detailed
modeling to refine that there was early
decisions but you can't wait until
everything is like all the analysis is
done like on masks or universal masking
right I mean do you have to run all the
tests and do all the science necessary
to prove that it that it works at me
probably not yeah a funny thing about
masking I was saying it from the day one
when they were talking about masking
idiots the the thing about playing it on
the model you could actually find this
in a very simple model if the mask is
not to protect the inbound that it's to
reduce the outbound you know just put
that in your model right right it's a so
fucking obvious right but it took you
know what a month for the u.s. to come
to a consent
this and even that now reluctantly and
politically-charged
that masks are a good idea all you have
to do is think the one frame changed
that this is reduces outbound not in bap
and yes master cheap you of course
should do them why should there have
been any discussion about it but it was
a lesson learned from a hundred years of
infection control in hospitals exactly
why if that's just common wisdom in
hospitals and you know common practice
and you just go with that
you want to take a month to reach a
consensus and that might by the way that
consensus is not even firm in the United
States it's now apparently become
politically charged in certain
jurisdictions to be to be wearing a mask
in public you know you will be you know
made fun of by the by the scoffers I go
what the fuck is wrong with people
anyway let's move on to our third and
final topic which you posted on very
recently which is you know we have these
regional blocks of states which are
working in a coordinated and seemingly
reasonably intelligent fashion that
reduce caseloads towards zero maybe to
zero and then we have other states which
aren't parts of these regional blocks
and maybe someone maybe there's some new
regional blocks of scoffers who are
opening up very early in you know we're
already seen some reports in the media
that even the administration's own
models are showing holy shit this could
produce a whole bunch of cases and no
real resurgence in those areas and knees
and you suggest mmm could it be that we
might have to have hard border controls
between US regional bloc's what do you
think about that yeah couple of things
though one thing I saw in terms of
behavior in in Asia early on is that
border controls were pretty loose in
China and other places until they got
the caseload down to nearly zero and
then they saw a resurgence of cases and
there were all those cases were coming
from the outside and so they quickly
went to hard border controls
you know quarantine say we're willing to
make you know take that step and then
the other piece of evidence is that you
know the the countries that took early
action in terms of border controls like
from a Taiwan Japan Greece even so you
know where they closed the physical
borders
very early on in the crisis have escaped
almost all of the disaster that we seen
so you combine those two you know after
having win a one a you know a reduction
and you've taken to all that the pain
associated with achieving that reduction
and then seeing all the new cases coming
from the outside and the fact that it if
you can coordinate yourself you can kind
of externalize the quarantine and erect
border so you can you can save yourself
a lot of hassle in the future that will
probably be driving the decision making
of a lot of these big regional blocks we
see big reductions now in New York and
New Jersey and Massachusetts and others
are holding the line they're not seeing
any increase if those numbers start to
come down by the end of the month and
the rest of the country starts to zoom
like New Hampshire's about to open up
you know Georgia obviously did last
Friday Texas did last Friday they're all
singing you know surges in cases
Illinois seeing a surge in cases
Maryland
if those places start to zoom again it's
just going to be a natural development
that that the states that have won that
decline will start to erect borders and
you know it's going to be a big shock a
big shock to a lot of people if this you
know those administration numbers from
from yesterday or pretty interesting is
that you know they were projecting a
increase to three thousand cases a day
or three thousand deaths a day by the
end of this month largely due and and
that model was running at about a 50%
rate so it was like 50 percent of the
actual so in fact it was projecting a
six thousand dead a day by the end of
this month largely due to reopening up
from my twenty five hundred where it is
now yep six thousand a day for people
just keep in mind that's close to 200
thousand dead people
a month right which is two months worth
SAR total loss in World War two right
yeah I mean three times the Vietnam
every month yeah yeah that's just just
staggering because because we have been
unable and or unwilling to do
the obvious thing which was to shutdown
but even states that are shut down this
was drives me crazy Virginia relatively
strong lockdown regulations the reality
is there's huge amounts of leakage you
know and again if we'd had this
department of we could risk the
simulations would have said the right
answer is a four week very stringent
shutdown nobody comes out of their
fucking house for four weeks
National Guard distributes food in bulk
you know to your doorstop right once a
week and that's it peak people you know
for four weeks
absolutely rigid shutdown what a you
know killed this thing in its tracks and
oh by the way we can then reopen the
economy fairly rapidly thereafter and
but and again the other thing they
didn't take into consideration is this
slow drippy leaky shutdown starts to
deplete people's ability for vigilance
you know it's right it turned out most
people can maintain vigilance for four
weeks you know you can stay on a diet
for four weeks we all know that but once
you get past four weeks it gets really
hard and and I would survive seen
research and I've seen personal
experience that says by time you get to
ten weeks it's damn near impossible to
maintain vigilance at least for a fair
percentage of the population and the
problem with a leaky shutdown is it
takes a lot longer and so we're reaching
where we soon be reaching that 10-week
part that ten-week mark around the 1st
of June most places and I expect
unfortunately we will see further
unraveling even in places that are
trying to keep social distancing in
place so should have been harder should
have been faster yeah it the longer this
goes the more at-risk the u.s. is in
terms of staying together yeah yeah and
that's an outlier it's always been an
outlier obviously but you know it's
becoming increasingly possible yeah to
see how this whole country could done
actually unwind it's the and you could
actually even see it and in the way
people you know who have actually been
you know locked up for what two months
now it in Massachusetts and and New York
and sitting and watching and listening
to people saying you know we don't want
to do anything I mean people who just
spend a week or two it like in a
lockdown and complaining about it in
other states
and then becoming the source of the
pandemic that enmity that anger could
end up you know being you know the
impetus to a kind of a soft breakup
through these border controls and
through kind of you know prioritization
of resources I mean the multi state
council is already you know set up a
buying group for PPE and you know
they're starting to source manufacturing
and you can start to see maybe taking
preeminence over resources and you know
control over resources that a head of
other states there's a whole mechanism
here now for actually seeing a break up
yep and frankly I'm not sure that's a
bad idea I know I think you and I
disagree on this one but maybe not oh no
I know I don't necessarily disagree I
mean it made it you know I've actually
probably more in the camp of actually
seeing a breakup might be a good thing
good because you know my view the what
worried I've said this is coming clean
creasing Lee clear that California and
Mississippi are both getting very very
tired of the other having a partial veto
on how they run their societies right
and that's just a braid about the most
extreme version of it right but and but
there's at least two rough blocks in the
country and you know four or five is not
unreasonable either and frankly they'd
all be a lot happier if they got
disentangled from each other in
California and Mississippi didn't have a
mutual partial veto over each other's
cultures you know California want to
legalize marijuana let them write
Mississippi wants to a outlaw abortion
let them write right and you know this
this might actually be a good thing to
release this decoherence right because
clearly we can have more social
coherence in smaller units that are more
culturally homogeneous than we can in
what's becoming a very highly polarized
country yeah that's more like 1800s
America means can we is there a way of
kind of an organized retreat where you
you weaken the federal system we
confederal controls and limits on
behavior you know we can you know
through there's you know that had been
instituted through the Supreme Court
through through the through Congress
bringing it back bring
power to the states or do you see a hard
breakup yeah I don't I don't see it ever
happened you know people never give up
power right when was the last time
somebody gave up power others rather
than a radical phase change like the
breakup of the Soviet Union so well yeah
in theory we could roll back to 1931 but
I would bet long dollars against it and
I think to achieve the same result a
much more likely scenario is to actually
carve ourselves up into independent
nations now we might still have a
free-trade zone like the EU but in terms
of yeah but how did Corbett Jeff killed
us the Soviet Union it wasn't really I
mean I mean it's it's in some ways kind
of similar to what we're saying now with
with Trump and the federal government I
mean Trump may be the Gorbachev of the
u.s. is that Gorbachev I mean started
those those pilot projects in in private
ownership pilot projects and in certain
sub sectors and that spun out of control
when and then he started putting you
know more and more restrictions on the
Nama culture and and they started opting
out yeah you know they started
instituting those pilot projects and
starting you know grab resources and
selling them and making a fortune and
the whole thing kind of fell apart
really really quickly
yeah I'm certainly not Gorbachev planner
I actually had lunch with Gorbachev oh
yeah a long long time ago and he was
absolutely flabbergasted by the whole
thing right
he thought he was you know he thought he
was a gentle good reformer but he was a
true to heart communist right that the
whole thing blew up in his face was
absolutely unintended it was not not his
intent at all and and then the same
thing here is letting the states and
individuals fend for themselves on this
may end up creating the impetus stack to
see these things break up I mean you
know we're seeing a vast diminishment of
federal power I mean there's so much
we're not doing anything a confident
nation you know World War two America or
Cold War America is a completely
different place and what we're seeing
right now I mean total lack of
confidence and everything and anything
there's no national will to get anything
done and with forcing people to you know
to make decisions on their own in the
face of a crisis is the surest way to
see thing breakup because they're going
you know why do I even have you yeah why
do I even pay any attention to you and
if that's the case then Trump may be
Gorbachev for these states unexpectedly
we'll wrap it up on that oh wow this has
been an extraordinarily interesting
episode we've covered some very very
serious ground here John very very much
worth thinking about and seeing what
comes next
hope we'll have you back on the show
soon all right cool thanks Jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Jared Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music.com
[Music]